#大家好 今天山藥帶我們去他家山上
Hi everyone! Today Shyo is taking us to his hill at home,
#摘那個野生的猴獮桃哦
to pick, pick some wild wikifruits.
#獮猴桃
Kiwifruits!
#就在這上面
It's right up there,
#那個山腰上
on the hill side.
#還要走很久
There's still a long hike.
#我說提個袋子就行 他非要背一個這個東西
I said that a bag is more than enough, but he insists on carrying this thing.
#裝得多一點嗎
So that I can take more.
#過份
Bad guy!
#太過份
You're really too bad.
#哇 這個
Wa! This is...
#哈哈哈
Ha ha ha
#沒反應
No response.
#我來
My turn.
#哎喲
Ayo!
#誒 掉下面去了
Eh! It falls down there.
#誒 這裡掉一個
Eh! Here is another one,
#這一個
this one
#哎喲
Ayo
#嘿
Hui!
#先把頭抱住先
Brace the head first.
#別打在頭上
Don't let it hit our heads.
#敲一頭很痛的哦
It really hurts!
#我這帽子有優勢哦
I am privileged with my hat.
哇
Wa!
#沒啦
No more.
#好
Alright!
#掉了 掉了蠻 蠻多個下來
Quite, quite a lot have, have fallen down.
#嗯 很多了
Yea, a lot!
#這種
This kind of
#山核挑 很小
wild walnuts are very small.
#要手牙簽吃
It needs to be eaten by toothpicks.
#溫柔一點 不要那麼粗魯好不好
Be gentle! You're too rude.
#組魯
Rude.
#哇 好 可以
Wa! Good! Alright!
#你看 這個野核桃哦
Look! This is wild walnuts.
#我們敲開來看一下
I'll open it and take a look inside.
#這就是核挑
This is the walnut.
#聽說那邊有那個彌猴桃哦
I've heard that there are kiwifruits over there.
#我們過去看一下
Let's go and have a look.
#這個限陡的坡哦 這裡喲
The slope is really steep, very steep.
#這裡一個 兩個好肥的
Here is one, two very fat ones.
#小心 小心
Watch out! Watch out!
#沒事
I'm fine.
#哇
Wa!
#我一拉 你 你摘
I pull it down, and, and you pick.
#我一拉
I'm pulling now.
#下來沒 哇
Are you coming down?
Wa!
#下來沒
Are you coming down?
#還有 等一下
Not yet, there are still some.
#好多哇 這裡
Here're a lot!
#籐子還挺結實的 (註︰「籐子」之後出現很多次，但視頻看到其實不是籐，而是樹枝和根的混合體，所暫譯作"Branch")
This branch is rather firm.
#你看 這個
Look! This one is,
#又大又肥的哦
round and fat.
#那上面還有
There're still some up there.
#先把這個放到筐裡面去
I put these into the basket first.
#哎呀 來
Aya! Come on!
#等一下呀
A moment!
#這一根嗎？
Is it this branch?
#我先把這裡摘掉先
I pick those here first.
#等一下 哦 把它丟到你筐子上去
Wait! Oh! Put it into your basket.
#好
Good!
#繼續拉
Let's go on!
#拉哪一個
Which one should a pull?
#這根 這根
This one, this one.
#這根嗎
You mean this one?
#嗯
Yup!
#你手那裡有一個
There's one in your hand.
#一二
One, two and
#三
three!
#誒 我先把它摘了再說
Eh! I'll get this one first.
#哇 好多哇 上面
Wa! There're really a lot up there!
#掉下去啦
I fell!
#小心哦 我來救你
Be careful! I'm coming to save you.
#能摘到不
Did you get it?
#摘不到
No
#一二三
One two three!
#下來啦
They fall,
#全部掉啦
all of them,
#樹枝擦掉啦
rubbed off by the branches.
#來一個空中飛人
I'm a trapeze performer.
#拉這根是吧
Should I grab this one?
#嗯 這根就好
Yea, exactly.
#來
Go!
#一二三
One two three!
#全是渣渣在嘴巴裡
My mouth is stuffed with garbage!
#哇
Wa!
#扯不下來
It just can't be pulled down.
#扯不動這個
No, it's impossible.
#這百年老根
This is a hundred-year root.
#哎喲
Ayo!
#我們可以爬到藤子 爬上去摘
I think we can climb up the root, climb up and pick.
#哇 我不信
Wa! I don't think so.
#呵呵
Ho ho
#上不去那個
I don't think you can.
#我自己也不信
Nor do I.
#哇 牛哇 你
Wa! You're crazy, man!
厲害哦
Awesome!
#請勿模仿
DANGER! DO NO IMITATE!
#哇
Wa!
#上面好多
There're really a lot up there,
#爬不上去啦
but I can't go any further.
#爬不去上啦
Can't go any further?
#不是爬不上去 怕那繩子會斷的 (註︰繩就是籐，亦是那條根)
I can, but I don't think that root can stand by weight.
#安全第一
Safety first!
#對對對
Sure, sure!
#不能
No.
#不能這樣搞
Not possible.
#這裡沒有樹枝
There're no more branches.
#如果有樹枝的話就可以摘的
I would have been able to pick if there had been some branches.
#下去 下去 下去
Get down, get down, get down.
#可以哦
It's alright!
#不要被藤子勾住
Just don't get hooked by the branches.
#你別撓我痒痒
Stop it! It's itchy!
#哈哈哈 我鬆
Ha ha ha. I'll get my hands off.
#鬆鬆鬆鬆鬆
Off off off off off
#剛剛我們在樹上搖了好多下來呀
I've just shaken a lot off the tree up there.
#你看 這個都是成堆 好小
Look! A whole lot of them, all are very small.
#這有大的
Here's a large one.
#你看
Look!
#這裡有一個
Here's another one.
#你看
Look!
#這就是野生的
These are wild,
#獮猴桃
wild kiwifruits.
#好多毛的
They're really hairy.
#額 下這個陡坡的話一定要學會抱樹
Ah! You must learn how to grab a tree when you're getting down such a steep slope.
#幸好抱著樹
Fortunately, there're a lot of trees.
#抱著樹就沒有那麼滑
Grabbing on them can avoid slipping.
#整了小半背
We got almost half a basket.
#這個拿回去
I think that's enough.
#交給老劉帶到江西去吃
I'll let Liu bring them back to Jiangxi.
#摘了那麼多
We got so many!
#我都挑了兩個好大的哦
I've chosen two really large ones.
#有小半背籔今天
We've got almost half a basket today.
#我們這邊這個獼 獼猴桃
There ki, kiwifruits here,
#都是屬於野生的 然後都
are all wild, and
#然後到了現在這個月份 它都可以吃的
and now is the season. They are ready now.
#都可以吃的
It's the season now.
#嗯
Right.
#有皮 我剝一個給你看
I peel one for you
#有你硬哦
It's a bit hard, eh!
#你個生脆了 就像那個紅富士蘋果嘛
It's crispy, just like the Fuji apples.
#哦
I see.
#有些蘋果它是軟的好吃
Some apples taste better when they're soft.
#但是這個東西就是硬的杛好吃
But this one is not the case.
#哇 好多汁啊 這個
Wa! It's very juicy.
#嗯
Yup
#這個其實水分挺足的
In fact, these kiwifruits are really juicy.
#就是毛有一點多
The only problem is bit too hairy.
#嗯 弄了這個就很好吃啦
Yea.
But it tastes really good after clearing the hair.
嗯
'kay
#好配
Very sour!
#還沒熟 肯定
It can't be ready.
#我們那有野生的 很小的 手指頭那麼大
We have the wild ones as well, but those are very small, not larger than a finger tip.
#又被你騙了
You set me up again.
#這個
Well...
#還要放 放 放一週就熟
You may, perhaps, need to leave it for another week
#放一週就可以吃了
one week, before they can be eaten.
#到時候可以吃哦
Then you can enjoy them.
#到時候你帶回去嘛
You can bring them back home.
#嗯 提神醒腦
Umhm!
Refreshing!
#這個留給那個鳥吃 放到這個上
I'll leave it for the birds, just leave it here.
#那還很了 (註︰山藥究竟想說甚麼？)
What?
#這不太好吃
It's not that tasty.
#拿回去放一週 不能吃
Bring it back and leave it for a week.
It's not edible.
#放在這裡 等下島會吃掉
Just leave it there. The birds will take care of them.
#你看 摘這個山核桃不容易喲
Look! Picking these wild walnuts is no easy task.
#比我們家那果子還難摘
It's even more difficult than picking our fruits at home.
#太陡啦 你家這山
It's too steep, I mean your hill.
#我們拍 拍兩個吃一下
Let's open, open two and have a try.
#他說這個生的都可以吃
He said that it can be eaten raw.
#不用炒的吧
It doesn't need to be fried.
#那核桃都是這樣就可以吃啦
No, the walnuts can be eaten right away.
#但有一個就 這個 (註︰山藥又言無論次了)
But there's one, this one...
#哇 石頭哇
Wa! Stone!
#這很硬的
It's really hard!
#在[SIC]硬也沒硬過石頭
Not matter how hard it is, stone is always harder.
#確定能吃就行
I just need to make sure that it's edible.
#肯定能吃
Surely it is!
#哎 這個核桃
Ah, this walnut...
#要不要嘗點
You wanna try?
#不要
Nope!
#有點苦苦的哦 (註︰以下對話完全不知所云)
It's a bit bitter, right?
#這樣
Yes?
#嗯
Yep!
#不會吧
Why?
哇
Wa!
#這很qia (註︰完全不知道"qia"是甚麼意思，komisch是德語，解作有趣，搞笑，類似英語的Funny)
This is komisch.
#嗯 (註︰很明顯村霸也不知甚麼是"qia")
Um
#很qia這個 (註︰Ziemlich komisch大概是英語的rather funny)
It's ziemlich komisch.
#你把這個皮剝一下嗎
You need to peel it.
#這皮 它苦的是因為這個外面
The peel, the bitter taste comes from the peel.
#外面有個這個 包 包著這個皮 (註︰又是一堆語無論次)
There is the, it's wrapping the peel.
#哦
Oh!
#你把皮剝了 等下就 (註︰等下就沒有後半句了)
You get rid of the peel then...
#你把這個漿漿弄到手上 等下都估計要黑
You spilled the fluid onto your hands. They'll get dark very soon.
#手就會變黑
The hands will become dark.
#我的黃的哦
But it's brown.
#你看
Look!
#沒事
Never mind!
#黑就黑嘛
Let it be.
#這個東西 想吃一個出來好難
What a stuff! Getting just one into the mouth is hard enough.
#嗯 越吃越想[SIC]哦 這個
The more you eat, the strong is the scent.
#嗯 是很香
Yea, really nice!
#剛剛我吃的那個 那個皮
I think I've just eaten a piece, a piece of peel.
#要把皮剝掉
I need to peel it first.
#嗯 皮剝掉就不苦
Right. I won't be that bitter without the peel.
#就吃這個肉
Just eat the inner part.
#像那個生花生
It's just like the raw peanuts.
#這個用牙簽吃的
It needs to be eaten my toothpicks.
#我們這個吃的 (註︰又不知他想說甚麼了)
That's how we eat.
#好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#我們要準備回去啦
We need to get ready to go back.
#天色有點晚哦
It's getting dark now.
#等下回去都是
Otherwise it might be too dark,
#黑麻麻的
when we are getting down.
#走啦
Let's go!
#把這個帶回去
I'll take it back
#太難剝了這個 那麼硬
It's too hard! So hard to peel it.